In this lesson, we're going to learn about read-only properties and optional properties
in TypeScript.
So these features help us protect our data and clearly express which values are acquired
and which are optional.
So in real-world applications, not "award" data should be changeable
and not "award" data is always available.
TypeScript lets us express both of these ideas directly in our types.
So let's first of all start off with some optional properties.
So optional properties are used when the value may or may not exist.
So let's define an interface or the user.
And we're going to have a few properties here.
First of all, ID, that's going to be a number.
Then we're going to have a name which is a string
and then an email but one the email to be optional.
We put that with a question mark after the name and then the type.
See the difference? We have a question mark and that means it's optional.
So again, any objects being created may or may not have this property.
As a quick example, if we have a user, let's say user one is of type user.
We can do an ID of one and a name could be Alice.
Use a mandatory.
Let's create a user so const user one of type user.
So we have an ID set to one and we have our name.
So Alice and it's into type these two properties, then that's okay.
If we want to create a second user of user two, change the name to Bob
and Bob has got an email address and now we can specify that email address
or Bob at example.com.
Both of these objects are valid but optional properties are perfect
for fields like email, phone address or maybe profile images.
If an optional property is missing,
it's value is going to be undefined.
So if we did something here and do console log
and we try and access user one's email address.
Let's execute that.
We're going to get that as undefined.
So now let's talk about read only properties.
So these properties can only be set once and they then cannot be changed afterwards.
So let's just remove this moment to find another interface.
It's an interface called product.
I'm going to have an ID property but this is going to be read only.
So we're going to specify this property only when we create a product.
So read only and then ID number.
Let me have any other properties like name string and maybe price.
So let's now create an object to const prompt dot to type product.
And its ID is going to be set as 101 name laptop
and price whatever we want.
Now if we try and change that so if we do product product ID
and set that to maybe 102.
Type script stand going to complain because it's a read only property.
Now a comma question is what's the difference between read only and const?
Now the key would const by CRNST prevents reassignment of variables
whereas to read only prevents reassignment of properties on objects.
So we defined so now we have a const here as a const product.
The object itself can't be reassigned but the properties can still change.
We can of course combine read only with optional.
So let's have an interface of maybe account as an example.
We're going to have a read only ID property just like we did on the product.
Using name upstream and an optional property with the email address of string.
Now maybe wondering what's the difference between having an optional property
and just having a property that we can set to find.
So if you have an example of say interface and this is just a straightforward one.
Let's actually have a call example.
And we're going to have a value which is an optional that is string.
What's the difference if we do for example a is type of example.
And we set this just to an empty object.
And we do const be is example.
We specify the value explicitly as undefined.
Now both of these are actually valid but the optional properties that we have here
where we specify it, it communicates our intent more clearly as you can see
because we are specifically setting the value as undefined.
Whereas where we have an empty object the value still gets set to undefined but it's not as explicit.
Now it's pretty much it for read only and optional properties.